בוקר טוב, Boker tov, good stay in the עומר, Omer, good מוצאי
פסח. Motzei Pesach. We pick up today on דף נ"א, Daf Nun
Aleph, 51, I mean that's the דף, Daf, but we pick up
on נ"ב, Nun Amud Bet, top of נ"ב, Nun Amud Bet, and
we are איתמר רב הונא, Itmar Rav Huna, so the line starts
with רב הונא Rav Huna about 12 lines down. We were dealing
with a lot of משניות Mishnaot about על מנת Al menat on
the condition that, and then a discussion about if somebody, if a
woman said, well even though we made the condition I was thinking
something else, it doesn't matter, דברים שבלב אינם דברים, Devarim shebalev einam
devarim, very all those very relevant discussions for issues about קידושי טעות
Kiddushei ta'ot which is an important question in עגונה Agunah issues. And
this most recent משנה Mishna dealt with the fact that the original
קידושין Kiddushin had been פחות משווה פרוטה Pachot mishaveh perutah and so
on, something that should have been pretty obvious it was not good,
and nevertheless we don't look at future acts like giving of gifts
and re-interpret them and translate them into a new act of קידושין,
Kiddushin, we say she's not married at all, which is also very
relevant because in some of these עגונה Agunah cases you run the
ways of dealing with this trying to discover if the original קידושין
Kiddushin had been not good, and then if the original קידושין Kiddushin
had been not good you don't look at anything that follows it
as an act of קידושין, Kiddushin, although as I mentioned I think
yesterday, there's actually a debate between רב משה Rav Moshe and רב
יהודה הרצל הנקין Rav Yehuda Herzl Henkin because the משנה Mishna talks
about like later gifts don't become an act of קידושין. Kiddushin. Rav
Henkin said that with actually sleeping together, having sex together in a
marital context, ביאה Bi'ah is a type of a קידושין Kiddushin act
that does not require as much intent to effect a קידושין, Kiddushin,
it's just the reality that they are having sex in a marital
context that itself creates like the קידושין, Kiddushin, you know just the
de facto reality, so he actually was much stricter about that, but
the general הלכה Halacha has followed רב משה, Rav Moshe, and that's
very important in these עגונה Agunah cases. So now the גמרא Gemara
continues with the following. איתמר Itmar was said, רב הונא Rav Huna
again on נ"ב Nun Amud Bet about 12 lines from the
top, 15 lines from the top, רב הונא אמר חוששין לסבלונות. Rav
Huna amar choshishin lesavlanot. Again against what the משנה Mishna seemed to
say, he said that if somebody basically sent gifts to his wife,
to his fiancée, רש"י Rashi says if you look at רש"י חוששין
לסבלונות מי ששידך באשה ונתרצתה. Rashi choshishin lesavlanot mi sheshidach be'isha venitratzes.
So רש"י Rashi has
to says it's not just in a vacuum, there has to be
some type of a context, they actually made an engagement and she
said yes, or he, you know what's that word, not
engagement, courted, you know and she agreed to it, okay anyway, וקדם
ושלח סבלונות בידים חוששין שמא קידושין הן. Vekadam veshilach savlanot beyadayim choshishin
shema kiddushin hen.
So she said yes I'll get married and then he sent these
gifts, we're concerned that that might be קידושין. Kiddushin. So there wasn't
an act of קידושין Kiddushin that we would say is all defined
by the original act, and if the original act was no good
these don't mean anything, but there was also not in a vacuum,
there was some discussion, some engagement, so are we to interpret this
as קידושין? Kiddushin? And he says we do. Now I should say
that there's a debate
of
רש"י Rashi says do we interpret this as an act of קידושין?
Kiddushin? תוספות Tosafot says that's not the question. The question is do
we say since he's sending סבלונות savlanot it's evidence that there must
have been an act of קידושין? Kiddushin? Okay so that's
the debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot. Okay so הונא אמר
חוששין לסבלונות, Huna amar choshishin lesavlanot, we're concerned about that this might
be קידושין Kiddushin or
indicate it. וכן אמר רבא, Vechen amar Rava, Rava similarly said חוששין
לסבלונות, choshishin lesavlanot,
we're concerned about that this might be קידושין Kiddushin or indicate it.
אמר רבא ומוסבינן אשמעתין, Amar Rava umosivinan ashmatin,
but we ask on our position, meaning this position that we're saying
that it might be קידושין, Kiddushin, what about the משנה? Mishna? The
משנה Mishna says אף על פי ששלח סבלונות אחר מכאן אינה מקודשת,
Af al pi sheshilach savlanot acher mikan eina mekudeshet, that even after
if there's סבלונות savlanot that happen after the קידושין Kiddushin they don't
count as קידושין. Kiddushin. Now there's an obvious difference, there there was
a bad קידושין Kiddushin that preceded, but let's see what אביי Abaye
says. אמר ליה אביי התם כדתני טעמא, Amar leh Abaye hatam kedetani
ta'ama, that's what אביי Abaye says, שמחמת קידושין ראשונים שלח. shemachmat kiddushin
rishonim shilach.
We know there was a קידושין Kiddushin and it was bad. Here
there was no previous bad קידושין Kiddushin that preceded, so either this
might infer that there was a good קידושין Kiddushin or it might
itself be a good קידושין, Kiddushin, it's a different case. Okay, איכא
דאמרי Ika de'amri some say, אמר רבא מנא אמינא לה, Amar Rava
mina amina la, how do I know my position that in a
case of a when it does when it comes without a previous
you know without a previous bad קידושין Kiddushin it should be okay
or it might indicate a קידושין? Kiddushin? מנא אמינא לה כדתני טעמא
Mina amina la kidetani ta'ama because our משנה Mishna says שמחמת קידושין
ראשונים שלח shemachmat kiddushin rishonim shilach that the only reason the סבלונות
savlanot are not a problem is because they came after a bad
קידושין. Kiddushin. Okay הא הכא הוא דטעי ha hacha hu d'ta'ei
so that's in the case of the משנה Mishna he's in error
because he's relying on the original act of קידושין. Kidushin. הא בעלמא
ha b'almam but if that didn't proceed הוה קידושין hava Kidushin it
would be קידושין. Kidushin. By the way, that sounds much more like
רש"י Rashi than like תוספות. Tosafot. It doesn't sound that in a
normal case it proves קידושין Kidushin took place, it sounds like in
an ordinary case where there's not a previous קידושין Kidushin to frame
the issues, this itself constitutes קידושין. Kidushin. Anyway, that's the debate of
רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot. But either way רבא Rava is not
saying it definitely is, the word חוששין choshishin means maybe it is
and she would require a גט. get. Okay, which as you can
imagine could be an interesting question about what happens when you give
the engagement ring after the, you know, oh let's get married and
here's an engagement ring, that's סבלונות savlonos after שידוכין, shiduchin, the agree
to get married and then you give a גט, get, right? So
is that all of a sudden a חשש קידושין? chashash Kidushin? Okay,
so maybe again, maybe that's case the context is clear that it's
meant as engagement and it's not meant as קידושין, Kidushin, but it
starts raising interesting questions. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara continues. The
גמרא Gemara says like this, הא הכא הוא דטעי ha hacha hu
d'ta'ei הא בעלמא הוה קידושין ha b'almam hava Kidushin דאביי לא מיבעיא
קאמר. de'Abaye lo mibaiya qamar. Now אביי Abaye who's questioning this ruling
would say no no no, the משנה Mishna it says is like
a more, it goes without saying. What does that mean? לא מיבעיא
בעלמא דלא נחית לתורת קידושין כלל, lo mibaiya b'almam delo nakhis letorat
Kidushin klal, if it was just סתם stam a sending of gifts
even after according to רש"י Rashi some discussion of getting married but
nothing that attempted to be an act of קידושין, Kidushin, so then
clearly if it's just gifts we just interpret it as gifts even
after some engagement. Okay, פשיטא peshita that wouldn't mean anything. אלא אפילו
הכא ella afilu hacha but even in a case like our case
of the משנה Mishna דנחית לתורת קידושין denakhis letorat Kidushin it's clear
that they are attempting to do קידושין, Kidushin, אימא הוה קידושין, eima
hava Kidushin, in that case maybe I should make interpret the סבלונות
savlonos as an act of קידושין. Kidushin. קמשמע לן kamashma lan na.
So it's an interesting question, is it better to have a bad
קידושין Kidushin to or to have no קידושין? Kidushin? By the way,
this also comes up in a case of a couple that never
had any קידושין. Kidushin. Jewish men and women had or let's say
they had a secular marriage or let's say, you know, no but
nothing that even attempted to be a Jewish marriage, and would we
say, well they're living together קידושי ביאה, kideishei bi'ah, right? Or would
we say, you know, and maybe it's even a more of a
problem than our משנה Mishna because in our משנה Mishna there was
a bad קידושין Kidushin that said anything afterwards doesn't count as an
act of קידושין, Kidushin, it was already framed at the beginning and
that was a bad one. Well what if there was nothing that
preceded it? Okay, does that make it better or worse? So that's
partially what's being debated between אביי Abaye and רבא. Rava. So רבא
Rava says or רבא Raba says rather that when with there's nothing
that preceded and there's some type of an act giving of gift,
either that's a signal that there was a קידושין Kidushin the way
תוספות Tosafot reads it or itself will interpret as a
קידושין, Kidushin, and אביי Abaye says no, anything that happens we will
not interpret as a קידושין, Kidushin, you know, and it's so our
משנה Mishna is saying that even if they were attempting קידושין Kidushin
we don't interpret something after that as קידושין. Kidushin. Certainly when there's
no clear evidence that they were attempting קידושין, Kidushin, we're not going
to interpret this act as an act of קידושין. Kidushin. But as
you're hearing as I'm giving you these examples, all of this is
extremely relevant for contemporary issues about, you know, can you sort of
say since the if the original קידושין Kidushin was no good or
if they never had a קידושין Kidushin that there's no need for
a
גט. get. Okay, well right, I mean they've because they've chose to
marry with secular law, not with halakhic קידושין. Kidushin. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like
this. מאי הוה עלה? mai havah alah? What was the condition? אמר
רב פפא amar Rav Papa באתרא דמקדשי והדר מסבלי, b'atra demikadshi vehadar
mesabli, in a place that normally they start with a קידושין Kidushin
and then they send these gifts, חיישינן, chashinan, then you're sending the
gifts, we're concerned that either again according to רש"י Rashi you wouldn't
send the gifts without קידושין, Kidushin, so the gifts themselves are קידושין
Kidushin or that it indicates that a קידושין Kidushin preceded. Again, there's
two ways of reading the גמרא.
Gemara. If you are saying they are קידושין, Kidushin, why are we
thinking over?
Because they are gifts somehow, it's not just סתם stam a random
gift. It's a gift that in the cultural context is understood to
be a gift that is given after קידושין. Kidushin. Okay, I don't
know exactly how, you know, probably presumably it was given in a
certain way, there was a certain type of a thing that was
given. We're not, it's not saying you gave a מתנה. matana. It
says you gave סבלונות. savlonos. So in a particular cultural context there
was an understanding, let's say everybody a week after the קידושין Kidushin
sent a, you know, sent a, you know, sent a case of
wine to the כלה's kallah family. And this guy sent a case
of wine without a קידושין. Kidushin. There was a particular context in
which it was normally assumed that this is the thing that is
given after קידושין. Kidushin. So how did he do this? There wasn't
a קידושין. Kidushin. So it must be, we're concerned maybe there was
a קידושין Kidushin we didn't know about or the way רש"י Rashi
says is maybe he meant this to also be the קידושין. Kidushin.
Right, that's what I don't understand. I understand תוספות's Tosafot point, you
know, but רש"י Rashi I don't understand. In other words, if he
he everyone else sends it as presents post-קידושין, Kidushin, right. So how
are you interpreting this as a קידושין? Kidushin?
Because nobody would have sent a post-קידושין Kidushin present if they did
not also want this to count as קידושין. Kidushin. I understand, I
understand what's pushing you for תוספות, Tosafot, but there are different ways
things in the גמרא Gemara that indicate like רש״י Rashi and indicate
like תוספות. Tosafot. Okay, so anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so if that's normally the practice, then we're concerned that this
might constitute
קידושין. kiddushin. Okay, or might indicate קידושין. kiddushin. חשינן. Hashinan. מסבלי והדר
מקדשי, Misavli v'hadar mikadshi, in places where first you send the gifts
and then you do קידושין, kiddushin, so obviously לא חשינן. lo hashinan.
The gifts don't mean anything. They're that the you know, it's not
a concern of קידושין. kiddushin. Now, the גמרא Gemara says, מקדשי והדר
מסבלי פשיטא, mikadshi v'hadar misavli peshita, if normally you do the קידושין
kiddushin and then you send the gifts, the גמרא Gemara says it's
obvious, I don't know if it's obvious, but anyway, if we're going
to be concerned obviously we'll be concerned in that case. Now the
גמרא Gemara says there's a whole question about the גירסא girsa here,
we're just going to read the גירסא girsa we have. לא צריכא
דרובא מקדשי והדר מסבלי, Lo tzericha deruba mikadshi v'hadar misavli, most people
first do the קידושין kiddushin and then do the gifts, ומיעוטא מסבלי
והדר מקדשי, u'miuta misavli v'hadar mikadshi, and some people first do the
gifts and then do the קידושין. kiddushin. מהו דתימא ניחוש למיעוטא, Mah
d'teima neichosh l'miuta, let me say that I will although it says
ניחוש neichosh sometimes ניחוש neichosh means let me be lenient. Okay, let
me assume that this falls into the minority case and these are
the people that give the gifts before the קידושין kiddushin because there's
ten percent of the community that does that and I don't have
to be concerned at all that there was a קידושין. kiddushin. קא
משמע לן, Kamashma lan, since ninety percent of the community first does
the קידושין, kiddushin, I have to be concerned in this case there
also was a קידושין. kiddushin. Okay, so there's a lot of different
גירסאות girsas there, but the basic point is that in a case
where there's like that the only time you're concerned is when the
gift is a particular type of a gift that always comes after
the קידושין kiddushin and therefore when that gift is sent, that could
signal that either קידושין kiddushin took place or it was meant to
constitute קידושין. kiddushin. So that's not exactly you can't exactly interpret that
to be relevant to like other cases, like if you talk about
the case of let's say the engagement ring, okay? So דווקא davka
the engagement ring is מסבלי והדר מקדשי, misavli v'hadar mikadshi, right, the
engagement ring is what's given before the קידושין, kiddushin, so obviously that
doesn't raise a concern let's interpret the engagement ring as a קידושין,
kiddushin, right? It's only would be a case in which there's a
cultural context that it's a type of a gift that comes after
an act of קידושין, kiddushin, only in that case are we concerned
that that might be either signal a קידושין kiddushin or constitute a
קידושין. kiddushin.
And I think in my mind it's important to distinguish חשש hashash
versus וודאי. vadai. I know חשש hashash means maybe, you know?
Right, right, all of this was חשינן. hashinan.
It's not like let's say she slept with another man, we wouldn't
say it's adultery and kill her.
Right, that's what I said, all this is חשינן. hashinan. We're מחמיר
machmir that it might have been. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. בעי מיניה רב אחא בר רב הונא מרבא, Ba'i minei
Rav Acha bar Rav Huna meiRava, so רב אחא בר רב הונא
Rav Acha bar Rav Huna asked רבא. Rava. הוחזק שטר כתובה בשוק.
Huchzak shtar ketubah bashuk. Now this case is תוספות Tosafot's biggest proof,
because this clearly is does a certain thing be evidence that something
else happened? Okay, it was known that in the marketplace whatever, that
a woman's כתובה ketubah had been written. מהו? Mahu? Is that evidence
that the fact that there's a כתובה ketubah written that קידושין kiddushin
must have taken place?
But nobody saw it, but they think it's there?
Or maybe it was seen being passed around. Okay, it's not exactly
clear what the הוחזק בשוק huchzak bashuk is. רש״י Rashi says שרו
שטר כתובה. sharo shtar ketubah. Okay, people saw a woman's כתובה. ketubah.
Okay, is that an indication that she must have had קידושין? kiddushin?
So what's the story? אמר ליה וכי מפני שמחזיק שטר כתובה בשוק
נחזיק בה כאשת איש? Amar lei vechi mipnei shemachzik shtar ketubah bashuk
nachzik ba k'eshet ish? Big deal! So you see a כתובה. ketubah.
That's not going to be nearly enough evidence to be concerned that
let's take a look, that we should assume that she's married. So
we're going to see why. מאי הוה עלה, Mai hava ala, what
was the conclusion? אמר רב אשי באתר דמקדשי והדר כתבי, Amar Rav
Ashi, b'atar d'mikadshi v'hadar katvi, you see the exact parallel with the
language of the previous סוגיא. sugya. In a place where קידושין kiddushin
always precedes the writing of the כתובה, ketubah, והדר כתבי שטר כתובה,
v'hadar katvi shtar ketubah, חשינן. hashinan. Now it does still doesn't prove
definite, you know, who knows what might have happened, maybe it was
pre-written or whatever, but nevertheless if the standard is קידושין kiddushin and
then כתובה ketubah and this כתובה ketubah has been written for this
woman, that creates a concern that she's מקודשת. mekudeshet.
כתבי והדר מקדשי, Katvi v'hadar mikadshi, if first of all they write
the כתובה ketubah and the קידושין kiddushin comes after, which is like
we do today, so לא חשינן. lo hashinan. Obviously it's not a
basis of concern. Now, so the גמרא Gemara says מקדשי והדר כתבי
פשיטא. mikadshi v'hadar katvi peshita. If they do the קידושין kiddushin and
then write the כתובה, ketubah, of course we're concerned! What other possibility
might there be? So the גמרא Gemara says no, לא צריכא דלא
שכיח ספרא. lo tzericha d'lo shchiach safra. Let's say it's a case
where the scribes are not very, you know, are not always available.
מהו דתימא ספרא הוא דאיתרמי. Mah d'teima safra hu d'isrami. So this
guy was planning on getting married in three months, but the scribe
happened to be in town today. So even though normally you write
the כתובה ketubah after, he got it written before because this was
when the scribe was available. קא משמע לן Kamashma lan that that's
not enough of a basis to say we're not concerned. Since the
norm is that the writing comes after, the presence of a כתובה
ketubah creates enough of a concern that she might be married. Again,
all of this depends obviously on the context. In a context where
it's common enough that there's כתובות ketubot written before the קידושין, kiddushin,
that would not be an issue.
And concern meaning you need to identify her as an אשת איש.
eshet ish.
Well, a ספק אשת איש, safek eshet ish, right.
The גמרא Gemara doesn't talk about her social status, does it?
Well, it sort of cuts at it depends on what the practice
is, whether it's first A, first B, you know? All right, yes.
If you say that it's first effort the קידושין kiddushin was not
was not appropriate, was not fulfilled.
Might have been fulfilling but it wasn't fulfilled. Yes.
Is he the only one who knows that and feels a need
to make it right, or is it general knowledge?
Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara was discussing before, like a קטן
katan is general knowledge. And even so, so that's a חידוש; chiddush;
even if it's widely known that it wasn't good, you know, that
might then we don't we don't say that you want the next
thing to be the act of קידושין. kiddushin.
So, you know, so that's I mean so so yeah, I mean
that's the גמרא's Gemara חידוש chiddush initially that it's not only that
oh wait he didn't realize even if it was obvious that it
wasn't good, we don't interpret the next act as the act of
קידושין. kiddushin.
We went through דפים dapim where we say קידשתי בזו וכנסתי בזו.
kiddashti bezo ve-khinasti bezo. Right? He has to make some sort of
statement when he gives those סבלונות? savlonos?
Well, I mean but there's a גמרא Gemara says I mean the
תוספות, Tosafos, sort of תוספות Tosafos says that's why רש"י Rashi said
that we're talking about שידוך shiduch because גמרא Gemara back on ו
עמוד א vav amud aleph said that עסוקין באותו עניין asukin be-oso
inyan doesn't always need a statement, like if the דעת da'as is
clear enough, you know. But you are right. I mean it could
be that the reason we're saying we don't are we're not concerned
about the סבלונות savlonos is because, you know,
you need it to be like sort of like the גמרא Gemara
before about, you know, דברים שבלב, devarim she-be-lev, you need things to
be a much clearer context even if you didn't realize it wasn't
קידושין kiddushin we're not going to turn something into קידושין kiddushin unless
it's much more clearly articulated or expressed, right? So right, that gets
to like I said why הרב הרצוג הנקין Rav Herzog Henkin says
well that might be true about קידושי כסף kiddushei kesef but קידושי
ביאה kiddushei biah might be of a different character in that regard.
Okay, so let's take a look at the next משנה. mishna. המקדש
אישה ובתה. ha-mekadesh isha u-vitah. Now another issue, we're moving beyond תנאים,
tnaiim, we're getting into other types of scenarios. So one scenario was
a very important question about the first קידושין kiddushin was not good,
do you interpret later acts that way? Now question which is less
common, of course, but a case about trying to marry somebody who
you're not allowed to marry. Okay, so המקדש אישה ובתה, ha-mekadesh isha
u-vitah, a man tries to marry at one moment a woman and
her and her daughter, which is obviously one of the עריות arayot
in the תורה. Torah. Now if it was sequential he'd be married
to the woman and then ten minutes later try to marry the
daughter it wouldn't take effect. But he tried to marry them both
at the same time. Okay, so או אישה ואחותה, o isha ve-achotah,
or two sisters. כאחת, ke-achas, in one moment like he gave one
of them money and said or gave a third party the money
to be קונה koneh and to do and to be מקבל mekabel
the קידושין kiddushin for these two women. אינן מקודשות, einan mekudashot, neither
of them are married. Okay, so since you can't since you haven't
identified one neither of them are married. They don't say ברירה breira
either? Right, or whatever. Exactly. מעשה בחמש נשים, ma'aseh be-chamesh nashim, there's
a story with five women, ובהן שתי אחיות, u-va-hen shtei achayot, a
group of five women among them were two women. Two sisters. Two
sisters,
excuse me, five women among them two sisters. וליקט אדם אחד כלכלה
של תאנים, ve-liket adam echad kalkalah shel te'enim, and a certain person
picked a basket full of figs. ושלהן הייתה, ve-she-la-hen haytah,
and now this is like a whole series of things why it
shouldn't be a concern of קידושין. kiddushin. It was, you know, it
was their figs, okay, ושל שביעית הייתה, ve-shel shevi'it haytah, and it
was שמיטה shmitah so maybe he didn't really own the figs or
whatever we'll see what the שמיטה shmitah issue is
about. Okay, ואמר, ve-amar, or maybe because it was שמיטה shmitah even
though it was theirs he was able to take possession of them
because it was הפקר, hefker, and anyway that's like an interesting detail
which we'll have to get back to. But the the key for
us is the end, ואמר הרי כולכן מקודשות לי בכלכלה זו. ve-amar
ha-rei kulchen mekudashot li be-kalkalah zo. Says, I'm marrying all of you
with this basket. וקיבלה אחת מהן ve-kiblah achas mehen and one of
them took the basket on behalf of all of you, על ידי
כולן, al yedei kulan, for the sake on behalf of all of
you. ואמרו חכמים אין האחיות מקודשות. ve-amru chachamim ein ha-achayot mekudashot. Well,
I don't know about the other three but the sisters aren't married
because since there's two sisters here he's trying to marry two sisters
at once neither of them are married. Okay, so let's take a
look at the גמרא Gemara to explain what this is based on.
מנא הני מילי, menani mili, where does this come from? אמר רמי
בר חמא דאמר קרא, amar Rami bar Chama de-amar krah, the פסוק
pasuk says: אישה אל אחותה לא תקח לצרור לגלות ערותה עליה בחייה,
isha el achotah lo tikach litzror legalot ervatah aleha be-chayeha, a woman
with her sister you shall not take to create enmity to against
them in their life. התורה אמרה בשעה שנעשו צרות זו לזו לא
יהיה לך ליקוחין אפילו באחת מהן. ha-Torah amrah be-sha'at she-na'asu tzarot zo
le-zo lo yiheye le-ka likuchin afilu be-achas mehen. So he wants to
say that's פשט pshat in the פסוק pasuk or one way to
read the פסוק. pasuk. אישה אל אחותה לקחת לא תקח isha el
achotah likach lo tikach when
you try if you try to take them both אישה אל אחותה
isha el achotah at the same time like לצרור litzror at the
moment when they become צרות, tzarot, you know. So if you're trying
to take them at the same time then לא תקח, lo tikach,
the קידושין kiddushin won't take effect. Okay, so that's like פשט pshat
in the פסוק. pasuk. Okay. זו לזו לא יהיו ליקוחין אפילו באחת
מהן. zo le-zo lo yiheye likuchin afilu be-achas mehen. אמר ליה רבא,
amar lei Rava, אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, אי הכי היינו
דכתיב וסוף, i hachi haynu de-ketiv ve-sof, how do you read the
end of the פסוק? pasuk? ונכרתו הנפשות העושות מקרב עמם, ve-nichretu ha-nefashot
ha-osot mi-kerev amam, that if you do this you get כרת kares
if you transgress this. אי קידושין לא תפסי בה כרת מי מחייב?
ei kiddushin lo tafsi bah kares mi mechayav? If you didn't marry
either of them, so you don't get כרת kares for sleeping with
two sisters, you get כרת kares for sleeping with the sister of
your wife's sister. You have to be married to one of them
to get כרת kares for having sex with the other one. So
if that's the scenario of the פסוק, pasuk, the פסוק pasuk is
telling you the קידושין kiddushin isn't binding with either, then there would
be no כרת. kares. Right? So clearly the פסוק pasuk is talking
about you married one, don't... sleep with the other one and then
you'll get כרת kares with the other one. Okay, so clearly it's
not sequential. אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, so rather רבא Rava
says, קרא בזו אחר זו. Kra bezu achar zo. Clearly the פסוק
posuk is sequential. So why where that's what's the basis of the
teaching of our משנה, mishna, that the קידושין kiddushin isn't חל chal
for like either of
them? ומתניתין כדרבה, Umasnisi k'derabba, like רבה's Rabba teaching, דאמר רבה, D'amar
Rabba, famous teaching of רבה, Rabba, which now we're going to focus
on: כל שאינו בזו אחר זו, אפילו בבת אחת אינו. Kol she'eino
bezu achar zo, afilu bevas achas eino. If something wouldn't work sequentially,
then it doesn't work at the same time. If you tried to
marry רחל Rachel and then afterwards you married לאה—or Leah we'll put
יעקב אבינו Yaakov Avinu aside—it wouldn't be חל chal for לאה. Leah.
So when he tries to do רחל Rachel and לאה Leah at
the same
time, since there's no sequence, and since for one of them it
definitely wouldn't work after the other, so then therefore you try to
do them both, it works for neither. Okay, so that's a principle
of כל בזו אחר זו אינו. kol bezu achar zo eino. If
it wouldn't work in sequence and then you try to do it
at the same time, since you can't choose at the same time
which is first and which is second, and it's never going to
work for the second one, then in that case it doesn't work
for either one.
Yes, Michael? I've asked this kind of question before and I never
knew what the answer is. So in the case of the תאומים,
teomim,
or,
you know, one of them, is the woman then later on trusted
to say, "Of course we're not מקודשת, mekudeshes, it was a joke,
he's giving us our thing, I just accepted it"?
No, I mean that gets to the דברים שבלב dvarim shebelev issue.
You know, you can't claim it's a joke. Now, if there's cases
of אנן סהדי anan sahadei and so on—and that happens, you know,
a lot, a lot of פוסקים, poskim, there's a whole huge literature
on somebody that gave a woman כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin before עדים
eidus and then they basically said, "Well, we were just kidding around."
And sadly, I mean it happened just a few years ago at
SAR. It happens a lot in these Modern Orthodox-type—I don't know, maybe
sometimes in the חרדי Chareidi high schools as well—but Modern Orthodox because
there's boys and girls in the same school and sometimes they, for
whatever reason, decide they're learning מסכת קידושין masechet kiddushin that year. So,
I'm serious, this happens like more than you would believe. And the
kids are kidding around and they say, "Oh okay, הרי את מקודשת
לי בטבעת זו," harei at mekudeshes li betaba'as zo, and then there
are two kids, and then, you know, there are two בר מצוה
bar mitzvah boys in the room or whatever. They had this case
a few years ago at SAR. You know, it happens, yeah, I'm
totally serious. It happens, I mean much, much more than you would
imagine. No, because you don't want to do that obviously, because then
she obviously can't marry a כהן kohen and all these types of
things. So you have to try to bring evidence that it was
clearly משטה, meshateh, it was clearly
דרך שחוק. derech s'chok. But the question is what to create sufficient
evidence, you know, because that's like the גמרא Gemara before about דברים
שבלב אינם דברים. dvarim shebelev einam dvarim. Well, why don't you just
say all the time it's דרך שחוק? derech s'chok?
No, she accepted it like under a חופה—you chuppah don't—so you accept
it, that's קידושין. kiddushin. So that's a yes. She doesn't have to
say yes. So that's it. You can't—on the one hand you can't
סתם stam say I was kidding around. On the other hand, sometimes
it's obvious, like what we talked about yesterday, דברים שבלב כל אדם,
dvarim shebelev kol adam, אנן סהדי, anan sahadei, it was obvious it
was דרך שחוק. derech s'chok. But,
you know, but what's—what's the sufficient threshold for that? A lot of
תשובות teshuvos in רב משה Rav Moshe about these scenarios. Okay, back
to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, איתיביה אביי, Eisavei Abaye, so this is
רבה's Rabba explanation that since if it happened in sequence it wouldn't
work with the second one, when it comes at the same time
and there's no first and there's no second, it doesn't work with
either. So let's see if this is true. איתיביה אביי, Eisavei Abaye,
המרבה במעשר פירותיו מתוקנים ומעשרותיו מקולקלים. Hamarbeh bema'aser, peirosav metukkanim uma'asrosav mekukalim.
You take extra מעשר. ma'aser. You have ten units of grain and
you take two units to serve as מעשר ma'aser as opposed to
one. Okay, so your grain is fixed because you did take ten
percent of your grain, but your מעשר ma'aser now is מקולקל, mekukal,
is a mixture of מעשר ma'aser and
טבל, tevel, right? So here basically, one, two,
three, four, whatever, five, six, seven, eight, nine... okay, here's my nine
units and I take ten and eleven as my מעשר. ma'aser. Okay,
so well let's say one of them, this one is מעשר, ma'aser,
fixes all of this, makes this מתוקן metukkan and makes this מעשר.
ma'aser. This one, let's say you knew which was which, it was
afterwards, this one would be part of all my other grain, my
טבל tevel grain, okay? So right now since I took both of
these as מעשר, ma'aser, it's a mixture of מעשר ma'aser and טבל
tevel mixed up. One of those units is מעשר ma'aser and fixed
this, and one of them is from grain that hasn't had מעשר
ma'aser taken and is טבל, tevel, so it's טבל ומעשר מעורבין. tevel
uma'aser me'uravin. The problem is you don't know which is which. Okay?
So but we treat it...
are we talking about a case where you have a hundred in
front of you and you took eleven?
No, because that might be a case of, right, that's like, that
might be a case of, what do you call it, of מעשר
וחולין מעורב. ma'aser v'chullin me'urav. But anyway, well I'd have to figure
that case out. But okay, let's not worry about that right now.
Anyway, so anyway in this case it's מעשר וטבל מעורבין, ma'aser v'tevel
me'uravin, but the question is that would be if you took them
sequentially, but you took them at the same time. Okay, so let's
take... but we treat it as if they were sequential and we
don't know which is which.
No, that's true, מעשר ma'aser is exact. So
by the sisters, if we would say well one worked and the
other isn't and we don't know which one, then by the sisters
we should say you're married to one and we don't know which
one. But what we don't. We say since we don't know which,
then you're not married to either. So since we should say here,
well we don't know which is מעשר Ma'aser and which is טבל,
Tevel, let's say they're both טבל. Tevel. Why don't we say that?
Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says ואמאי, v'Amai, why is this true?
נימא כל שאינו בזה אחר זה, Naima kol she'eino be'zeh achar zeh,
since you can't do one after the other, since you can't take
a מעשר Ma'aser after a מעשר, Ma'aser, so אפילו בבת אחת אינו.
afilu b'vat achat eino. So when you do them at the same
time, the second one isn't מעשר, Ma'aser, so the first one shouldn't
be מעשר Ma'aser either. I mean, they're both at the same time.
You can't pick which is which. They're both. Why don't we say
they're both טבל? Tevel? So
אמר ליה, Amar lei, no, שאני מעשר דאיתא לחצאים. Shani Ma'aser d'ita
l'chatzayim. מעשר Ma'aser is different because it can come halfway. What does
that mean? דאי אמר תקדש פלגא דחיטתא, D'ei amar tikadesh palga d'chitata,
if
you would say every half of each grain is מעשר, Ma'aser, קדשה,
kadsha, it would work. So let's say here, these two things basically
saying, you don't in a way have to choose, because basically if
you have, I don't know, if each one of these units is
a hundred grains, okay, there's a hundred grains in each unit, literally
you know like kernels, okay, and this has a hundred grains. It's
not like oh there's a hundred grains that's מעשר Ma'aser and a
hundred in טבל Tevel and we don't know which one. No. All
two hundred are מעשר. Ma'aser. Half of every single grain of all
the two hundred grains are מעשר. Ma'aser. So therefore in a certain
way what we're saying is it's you don't in this case have
to say like it happened on one pile and not the other
and we don't know which pile. There's a way conceptually to say
it happened to the whole pile. All the grains were מעשר, Ma'aser,
half of each grain. And since you could say that about the
whole pile, therefore we're allowed to say that it worked. Okay, but
you can't say half of each sister is married to me. Okay,
you have to pick which one, and since you didn't know which
one, you say it doesn't occur to either. All right, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. The better half, right? Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, והרי מעשר בהמה? v'Harei Ma'aser Behema?
How about מעשר בהמה? Ma'aser Behema? דליתא לחצאים, d'leita l'chatzayim, you can't
have half of an animal מעשר בהמה. Ma'aser Behema.
It's a very very nice comparison.
מעשר בהמה Ma'aser Behema to the קדושין? Kiddushin? No, מעשר בהמה Ma'aser
Behema to מעשר Ma'aser grain for now. וליתא בזה אחר זה, v'leita
be'zeh achar zeh, and it can't happen sequential. Once you take one
animal as מעשר, Ma'aser, you walk them through the gate, the new
animals that are born, the tenth one is מעשר. Ma'aser. If you've
made the tenth one מעשר, Ma'aser, the eleventh one doesn't become
מעשר. Ma'aser. Okay, ואמר רבא, v'Amar Rava, יצאו שנים בעשירי, yatzu shnayim
b'asiri, that two animals, you did nine animals walk out of the
gate, and then when the tenth one was supposed to walk out,
two walked out at the same time,
okay, וקראן עשירי, v'karan asiri, and you called them both ten. You
said to both of them at the same time, okay. So one
of them is ten, one is eleven, but you called them both
ten, and they can't both be ten. And so why don't you
say, well since you don't know which one is, neither is. No,
you don't say that. You say עשירי ואחד עשר מעורבין זה בזה.
asiri v'achad asar me'uravin zeh be'zeh. Ten and eleven are mixed up.
One is one, one is the other, you don't know which is
which. And then you have to figure out how that works in
terms of bringing it as a קרבן korban or waiting for a
מום, mum, that we're not going to worry about that. But basically
that seems like a really nice parallel. So say here too, one
of the sisters is married to you, you just don't know which
one. So the גמרא Gemara says no, שאני מעשר בהמה דאיתא בטעות.
shani Ma'aser Behema d'ita b'ta'ut. מעשר בהמה Ma'aser Behema is different because
number ten will be מעשר Ma'aser even if you miscounted it. Okay,
and therefore because there's something about the objective fact that it is
the tenth that defines it as מעשר, Ma'aser, your non-designation or your
wrong designation is not as consequential. It's not all dependent on you.
It happens somewhat automatically. Okay, דתנן, d'tnan, like we taught in the
משנה, Mishnah, I mean to some degree it depends on you but
anyway, קרא לתשיעי עשירי, kara l'tshi'i asiri, if you have they were
walking out of your gate and you sort of got all confused,
all פערטומעלט. fertumult. So when nine walked out you said ten. Then
you oh, no, no, no, that wasn't ten. So עשירי, Asiri, then
the tenth walked out and you said nine to number ten. ולאחד
עשר עשירי, u'l'achad asar asiri, and then eleven you said ten. שלשה
מקודשים. shlosha mekudashos. Okay, they're all קדוש, kadosh, but only one of
them, it's very confusing. Anyway, they're all קדוש kadosh but they're not
all מעשר, Ma'aser, only the tenth one is מעשר Ma'aser in that
case. The other two have קדושה kedusha like שלמים, shlamim, but the
bottom line is is that even though you called number ten nine,
it still had קדושה, kedusha, it still became מעשר. Ma'aser. So in
that case, since to some degree it's going to be מעשר Ma'aser
by virtue of being the tenth, when you called ten and eleven
ten, we don't say well neither of them. You can't happen to
both so neither of them. Because even if there's obviously some error
here, one of them is going to be number ten. So that
works a little bit easier, okay, whereas again, so one case it
works easier because both of the whole pile, all twenty, all you
know, two hundred pieces of grain could all be מעשר, Ma'aser, half
of each grain. So therefore it can work together. This case can
sort of work together because to some degree even if you made
a mistake how to count it, it's still going to be מעשר.
Ma'aser. But in a case where it's all dependent on you and
it can't happen to both, we'll say it'll happen to neither. Okay,
so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
והרי תודה דליתא בטעות. v'harei Todah d'leita b'ta'ut. What about one minute?
The bread of the... Associated with a קרבן תודה korban toda that
that will not work if it's in error, וליתא דנמי בזה ובזה,
v'leisa d'nami b'zeh v'zeh, it won't work one without the other, with
every קרבן תודה korban toda you would bring forty loaves of bread,
thirty מצה matza and ten חמץ, chametz,
and you wouldn't bring the חמץ chametz on the מזבח, mizbeach, you
don't bring חמץ chametz on the מזבח, mizbeach, but anyway, you would
שחט shacht the קרבן תודה korban toda and you would have כוונה
kavana with the שחיטה shechita of the קרבן תודה korban toda that
that would sanctify the loaves of bread, they would be seen as
connected to the קרבן תודה, korban toda, and there would be forty.
Now, if you were in error, you were thinking about a different
forty loaves than the ones that were brought or sanctified or whatever,
then the ones that were intended for the תודה toda would not
become קדוש, kadosh, it doesn't work if it's in error. It also
doesn't work בזה ובזה. b'zeh v'zeh. After you slaughter the תודה toda
and sanctify forty loaves, extra loaves cannot become קדוש. kadosh. Okay, so
there's no, it won't work by itself by error, it won't work
בזה ובזה, b'zeh v'zeh, and here's the case. ואיתמר V'itmar
and it was taught,
תודה שנשחטה על שמונים חלות, toda she'nishcheta al shmonim challot, somebody brought
eighty חלות, challot, okay, and you שחט shachted the תודה toda on
twice the amount. So we should say, following the logic, that since
it can't work on forty of them, then it doesn't work on
the second forty, it doesn't work on any forty because you don't
know which is which, like the two sisters. Okay, חזקיה Hizkiya אמר
amar קדשי ליה ארבעים מתוך שמונים, kadshei lei arbaim mitoch shmonim, forty
are sanctified, you just don't know which ones. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
אמר amar לא קדשי ליה ארבעים מתוך שמונים, lo kadshei lei arbaim
mitoch shmonim, none of them are. So at least according to חזקיה
Hizkiya that contradicts רבא. Raba. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is consistent, but
חזקיה Hizkiya says it still works. So how do you explain חזקיה?
Hizkiya? So the גמרא Gemara says לוא איתמר עלה, lav itmar alah,
what was taught about that, אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi הכל מודים כל היכא דאמר קדשי ליה ארבעים מתוך
שמונים, hakol modim kol heicha d'amar kadshei lei arbaim mitoch shmonim, everybody
agrees that if you say forty out of the eighty should be
sanctified, קדשי, kadshi, that it would work, okay, because you're not trying
to sanctify the whole eighty, you said forty of them. You just
didn't specify which forty. That's different. That's like if you were to
take the two sisters and say I'm marrying one of you, I'm
not saying which one. Okay, so then it works. We have some
forty, we don't know which forty, but you're not trying to do
both, you're only trying to do one, that works. You just don't
know which one. Okay, לא יקדשו ארבעים אלא אם כן קדשי שמונים,
lo yikdeshu arbaim ela im ken kadshi shmonim, I'm not sanctifying forty
unless it works for all eighty. I only want it to work
for everything and I don't want it to work halfway. In that
case, לא קדשי, lo kadshi, everybody would agree it would not work.
Since it can't work for everything, it doesn't work for any. And
we're assuming that the case of the two sisters is implicitly that:
I'm marrying both of you. Okay, so what's the debate? לא נחלקו
אלא בסתם. Lo nechelku ela bistam. You didn't specify. You just said,
you just brought your eighty loaves, you didn't say what you were
doing. מר סבר לאחריות קא מכוין, Mar savar l'achrayus ka mechaven, that
basically the purpose of the eighty is you only want forty to
be sanctified and the other forty are a backup, but your intent
is only for forty to be sanctified and therefore forty are sanctified.
ומר סבר, U'mar savar, and the other one says, no, לקרבן גדול
קא מכוין, l'korban gadol ka mechaven, you're trying to make all eighty
and therefore it doesn't work. So bottom line, the way that we've
explained why חזקיה Hizkiya says that forty are sanctified is because we
say fundamentally you were only trying to sanctify forty. Okay, but if
you're trying to do it on both, neither works. So we have
now basically dealt with some very good challenges to רבא, Raba, but
the גמרא Gemara is asserting רבא's, Raba the logic of רבא's Raba
position, that the point is, if it won't work sequentially, then when
you do it at the same time and you're trying to do
it to both and you haven't specified which is which, since it
can't work for one of them, it doesn't work for either of
them. Okay, there are exceptions to the rule when things will work
by themselves בטעות, b'ta'os, or when things can work even on a
half grain, okay, but fundamentally if you're trying to do it to
both and it can't work for both and you haven't specified any
order then it doesn't work for either. That's רבא's Raba position. Yes.
It's מצה matza has to be exact, yes, and if you're doing
it on a half grain, what's the other half of it?
So that is still מצה matza and טבל tevel mixed together. Okay,
that's the conclusion, but because, but we don't say that well, it
shouldn't work at all because you didn't specify which. I did specify
which: all the grain is מצה, matza, half of each one. So
I mean you could say you didn't specify which half, but somehow
because you're dealing with all of the grain that's seen as not
the exact same situation.
But what do you give both of them? All of it? Even?
No, now you're, now you're stuck. Now what you have to do
is you have to take other grain to be מפריש mafrish on
the half that's the טבל tevel of the מצה matza grain. Okay,
that's why it says it's מקולקלים, mekulkalam, right, that what you give
the לוי Levi now is a mess, he can't, right now it
can't be eaten, it has to be fixed. Yeah.
So according to חזקיה's Hizkiya position, he might hold דברים שבלב דברים.
d'varim she'ba'lev d'varim.
No, I mean look, that issue of דברים שבלב אינם דברים d'varim
she'ba'lev einam d'varim is always the question because you know sometimes it's
not like it's, דברים שבלב אינם דברים d'varim she'ba'lev einam d'varim is
when you clearly, when, when the presumption like there's a clear presumption
of a certain thing and then should we insert in also what
you're thinking. But there are cases where it's not at all clear
what you're intending. I just brought eighty loaves. So דברים שבלב אינם
דברים, d'varim she'ba'lev einam d'varim, okay, let's say we say that, therefore
what? Therefore you only meant forty or therefore you meant all eighty?
There's no default. דברים שבלב אינם דברים D'varim she'ba'lev einam d'varim means
we can't insert, trying to guess what you're thinking to change our
default assumption of the case. There's some cases that there's no default
assumption. We have no idea what you meant by this. You brought
eighty loaves, you were supposed to bring forty. What were you thinking?
Who the heck knows? What did you mean by it? So, okay,
we can't go by what you're thinking. Then what should we assume?
We have to assume something, right? So דברים שבלב אינם דברים Devarim
Shebalev Enam Devarim does not mean that we never try to figure
out a case that's not explicit, because there are a lot of
cases that are inherently ambiguous and we have to try to give
it a הלכה halacha meaning. All right. Now whether we really in
those cases are trying to guess at what somebody's thinking, or what
we're really trying to say is the law is going to define
how the case, how that case is treated, I would agree with
that because if what they're really saying is חזקיה ורבי יוחנן Chizkiyah
VeRabbi Yochanan say, no, I bet this is what he's thinking, then
the obvious question is, well why don't we ask? Why don't we
look for other contextual clues? Why isn't it a different based on
the circumstances? So at the end of the day, what they're really
saying is since we don't know what he's thinking, we have to
decide what he's thinking. Okay, we have to just come up with
a rule about how to try to treat that case. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, ורבא למה לי לשנויי
כרבה? VeRava lama lei leshnuyei keRabbah? Now why did רבא Rava explain
like רבה Rabbah that the explanation of our משנה mishnah was if
it doesn't work sequentially, it doesn't work at the same time, right?
That's what רבא Rava said. רבה Rabbah made a general statement, not
about our משנה. mishnah. Things that don't work sequentially don't work at
the same time. He says that's why you can't marry two sisters,
neither of them are married. Why do you have to give that
answer? There's a better answer. What's the better answer, or the answer
that we're going to see in a minute that's רבא's Rava's own
position? תיפוק
ליה, Teipuk lei, קידושין שאינה מסורה לביאה נינהו. Kiddushin She'eina Mesura LeBiah
ninhu. So we're about to see in one minute, literally the next
line, that רבא Rava is of the position that a קידושין kiddushin
that can never be הלכתית halachically consummated is not a קידושין. kiddushin.
Now, what that means is, even if I didn't do it at
the same time. Okay, if I went over to two sisters and
I am saying I'm marrying one of you, okay I didn't say
which one, or maybe that sounds a little bizarre so here's another
case. I go to a father and I say I want to
marry your daughter, and he has two daughters. And he says great,
and he takes the money, and we didn't say which daughter. Okay,
so would you say I've married to one of them and I
don't know which one and I have to give a גט, get,
or do you say, no, that's a case I only wanted to
marry one? Or do you say, no, because since I can't have
sex with either one because why not? Because it might be the
other one that I'm not married to and then it would be
the איסור עריות. Issur Arayot. So therefore the קידושין kiddushin is never
binding because it's a קידושין kiddushin that can never lead to consummation
because there's a possible איסור עריות Issur Arayot it might be the
other one and I would never know. That's called קידושין שאינה מסורה
לביאה. Kiddushin She'eina Mesura LeBiah. So the גמרא Gemara says since that's
רבא's Rava's position in general, you don't have to say the problem
in the משנה mishnah was that they were at the same time.
The משנה mishnah would be a problem even if it was only
one of them and you didn't know which one, even if it
wasn't at the same time. It has nothing to do with them
being at the same time. There's an easier answer. It's a קידושין
kiddushin when it's not clear which one that can never be consummated.
So why isn't that the issue? So
the גמרא Gemara says לדבריו דרמי בר חמא קאמר. Lidvarav deRami bar
Chama ka'amar. No, he's just saying according to רמי בר חמא Rami
bar Chama that didn't take that approach that קידושין שאינה מסורה לביאה,
Kiddushin She'eina Mesura LeBiah, he said even if you don't believe, agree
with me in general, you can't do them both at the same
time. If you're trying to do both of them, since one of
them it won't work, it won't work for either. My position is
you can't even do one if you don't know which one. But
you certainly can't do both because then if it doesn't work for
number two, it's not going to work for number one. Okay, now
this is the segue to get into רבא's Rava's position which is
even further goes further than the משנה. mishnah. So let's take a
look.
The question now that's a ridiculous question I think, but the גמרא
Gemara doesn't care about יעקב אבינו Yaakov Avinu and the two sisters?
No, here it doesn't. I mean whatever, that gets discussed elsewhere. I
mean that was before מתן תורה Matan Torah or whatever. Okay fine.
איתמר, Itmar, קידושין שאינה מסורה לביאה. Kiddushin She'eina Mesura LeBiah. Now, now
we're going to talk about this. A קידושין kiddushin that cannot ultimately
be consummated הלכתית. halachically. Okay, אביי אמר, Abaye amar, הוי קידושין, havi
kiddushin, it still takes place, takes effect. רבא אמר, Rava amar, לא
הוי קידושין, lo havi kiddushin, it doesn't. Now by the way, how
about a question which is
חופת נדה? Chuppat Niddah? Meaning there's a whole interesting question about חופת
נדה. Chuppat Niddah. And when is a נדה niddah during the חופה?
chuppah? According to the רמב"ם, Rambam, he says it's not a real
חופה chuppah and you don't make
שבע ברכות. Sheva Brachot. I mean ספרדים Sefardim don't פוסק pasken that
because if they did obviously it would be a big problem, right?
What, we're going to have a whole wedding and not make שבע
ברכות? Sheva Brachot? Have announced to everybody that the woman's a נדה?
niddah? But anyway, but that's חופת שאינה מסורה לביאה Chuppat She'eina Mesura
LeBiah because for חופה chuppah is the נישואין nissuin is when they're
supposed to now be consummating their marriage, right? This is when the
marriage is supposed to translate into the fully lived marriage and the
whole idea of חופה chuppah according to some is ייחוד, yichud, privacy,
the ability to have sex and so on, to be in private,
to share domicile, to be intimate and so on. So that's like
a different question. But here we're talking just about the קידושין, kiddushin,
just the on-paper marriage, not yet the lived marriage. But nevertheless, even
though we're just talking about the קידושין, kiddushin, maybe if the קידושין
kiddushin can never translate to the נישואין, nissuin, can never translate to
a life of physical intimacy and of sex, then it's not even
binding as קידושין. kiddushin. Okay, but again I want to emphasize that
there's a חידוש chiddush here that we're talking even at the earlier
stage of קידושין kiddushin when you're not really yet up to the
stage of sex, but if it can never ultimately lead to
that then. Right, right. So, yeah, the question here is a case
of never. חופת נידה, Huppat Niddah, on the one hand, right, it's
more of a problem there because you're talking about נישואין, Nisuin, and
because it's more of a problem talking about נישואין, Nisuin, it means
even at that moment, if they can't be having sex because she's
a נידה Niddah according to this position of the רמב"ם. Rambam. So
here, the חידוש Chidush is that we're not talking about that, we're
talking at an earlier stage of קידושין, Kiddushin, which is just an
on-paper marriage, maybe that shouldn't be as relevant, and because it's not
as relevant, like נידה Niddah is certainly not a problem. The only
thing that possibly is a problem here is this case when it
will never be able to translate.
Even in the case of חופת נידה, Huppat Niddah, we still say
that
the קידושין Kiddushin are ודאי. Vadai. Yeah, yeah. Nobody ever questions קידושי
נידה Kiddushei Niddah is ודאי.
Vadai. You have to find another reason to invalidate it.
Exactly, exactly. So, but a hundred percent. So okay, but here it's
a קידושין Kiddushin that can never lead to consummation. Is that going
to be good?
איתמר: Itmar: קידושין שאינם מסורים לביאה, Kiddushin she'einam mesurin l'biah, אביי Abaye
says הוי קידושין, havei Kiddushin, it still works. רבא Rava אמר לא
הוי קידושין, amar lo havei Kiddushin, it doesn't work. And the case
that we're going to see is this case where somebody doesn't know
which sister he married. So it's a something that can never be
clarified, and therefore he can never consummate because he always might be
having sex with a sister, with his wife's sister. So אמר רבא
בר הינא, Amar Rava bar Hina, אמר רבא, amar Rava, so Rava
said: בר הינא אסברה לי, Bar Hina asbra li, Bar Hina sort
of explained to me this position of mine on a פסוק, pasuk,
which is the following one: כי יקח איש אשה ובעלה. Ki yikach
ish isha u’be’alah. If a man takes a woman and has sex
with her, קידושין המסורין לביאה הוו קידושין. Kiddushin hamesurin l'biah havu Kiddushin.
So כי יקח ki yikach has to be able to ultimately lead
to ובעלה. u’be’alah. It has to be able to be given over
to ביאה. biah. Okay, קידושין שאינם מסורים לביאה, Kiddushin she'einam mesurin l'biah,
if it can never lead to ביאה, biah, לא הוו קידושין, lo
havu Kiddushin, it doesn't take effect. Now, I just want to pause
for a second, because תוספות Tosafot asks the obvious question, which is,
well then why should
קידושין באיסורי לאווין, Kiddushin b'issurei lavin, you know, work? Right, when it
says like a כהן Kohen can't marry a גרושה Grusha or an
אלמנה, Almanah, right, why does that work? That's not, you know, there
it's not מסור לביאה, masur l'biah, you're not supposed to be having
sex, because of the קידושין. Kiddushin. So, so he, so he, so
he doesn't exactly give an answer according to רש"י. Rashi. One could
speculate, well, it's not as אסור assur as כרת, karet, but we
mean like it's a complete, you know, complete, considered a huge violation.
We could also say that by those types of things, by the
cases of like ממזר Mamzer and כהן גרושה Kohen Grusha and כהן
גדול אלמנה, Kohen Gadol Almanah, the primary איסור issur as framed in
the תורה Torah is not an איסור issur of sex but an
איסור issur of marriage. Right, the תורה Torah says like לא יקח,
lo yikach, right, אשה גרושה מאישה לא יקחו. isha grusha me'ishah lo
yikachu. So maybe that's very different when the, even though the primary
איסור issur is framed in terms of the marriage as opposed to
being framed in terms of the sex. Nevertheless, because of this question,
תוספות Tosafot suggests a different read of קידושין שאינם מסורים לביאה. Kiddushin
she'einam mesurin l'biah. תוספות Tosafot actually says it is the act of
קידושין Kiddushin itself that makes the ביאה biah prohibited. Meaning, if I
never would have married this one sister and I don't know which
one, then I could have had sex with her. Because, right, the
איסור issur is created as opposed to a case of my sister,
right, the קידושין Kiddushin doesn't create—if there was a woman that I
don't know, here's a case: I didn't know like, you know, somebody
didn't know whether this person was his sister or not, right, and
it was not knowable. A woman had a child, didn't know who
the father was, it might have been my father, this woman might
be my sister. If I do קידושין Kiddushin with her, is it
ספק קידושין safek Kiddushin or not? Or would you say, well, it's
אינם מסורים לביאה, einam mesurin l'biah, it's, you know, never be able
to have sex because she might be my sister. So רש"י Rashi
might say that would be a case of אינם מסורים לביאה. einam
mesurin l'biah. תוספות Tosafot says it would not, she'd be ספק מקודשת,
safek mekudeshet, because the case of קידושין מסורין לביאה Kiddushin mesurin l'biah
is the act of קידושין Kiddushin is what makes it forbidden to
have sex with her. When I marry one of two sisters, it's
only because I did an act of קידושין Kiddushin that I now
can't have sex. Is that clear? Because the only איסור issur is
sex with my wife's sister. The other case would be אשה ובתה,
isha u'vitah, a woman and her daughter. Only because I, if I
married a woman and one of the two, a woman and her
daughter and I didn't know which one, it's only because of the
act of קידושין Kiddushin that I can't have sex with them. Okay?
So תוספות Tosafot says קידושין שאינם מסורים לביאה Kiddushin she'einam mesurin l'biah
is not just that sex isn't possible, because there's other cases, איסורי
לאווין issurei lavin where it certainly takes effect. The case I gave
you, somebody might be a sister and we don't know, okay, ספק
safek it's the sister and we can't figure it out, תוספות Tosafot
would say that would be a ספק קידושין. safek Kiddushin. The case
here is that the קידושין Kiddushin created the איסור ביאה. issur biah.
If the קידושין Kiddushin is what makes ביאה biah impossible, that can't
be a type of a קידושין. Kiddushin. Okay, so that's a nice
more nuanced read of that. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues
like this: תנן, Tnan,
we taught in a משנה: Mishna: המקדש אשה ובתה, Hamkadesh isha u’vitah,
if a man marries a woman and her daughter, או אשה ואחותה,
o isha v’achotah, or two sisters, כאחת, k'achat, both at the same
time, אינן מקודשות, einan mekudashot, they're not married. הא אחת, Ha achat,
from אשה ובתה isha u’vitah or אשה ואחותה, isha v’achotah, it sounds
like if he married one and he didn't know which one, מקודשת,
mekudeshet, it would work. The only problem is that they were at
the same time.
But if he didn't know which one, then what would you do?
You'd have to give a גט. get.
You'd have to give a גט get to each one. ואמאי, V'amai,
why would that work? קידושין שאינם מסורים לביאה נינהו. Kiddushin she'einam mesurin
l'biah ninhu. It's not, it's a קידושין Kiddushin that won't be able
to translate into sex. תיופתא דרבא, Tyufta d'Rava, it's a clear contradiction
according to רבא, Rava, that's exactly the case that רבא Rava said
doesn't work, and the משנה Mishna implies that it does. So the
משנה Mishnah says it only doesn't work if they're at the same
time. So אמר לך רבא, amar lach Rava, רבא Rava would say
to you,
ולטעמיך אימא סיפא, v'letameich eima seifa, let's look at the end of
the משנה. Mishnah. מעשה בחמישה נשים ובהן שתי אחיות וליקט אחד כלכלה
של תאנים ושלהן היתה ושל שביעית היתה ואמר הרי כולכם מקודשות לי
בכלכלה זו. Ma'aseh b'chamisha nashim u'vahen shtei achayot v'liket echad kalkala shel
te'enim v'shelahen hayta v'shel shevi'it hayta v'amar harei kulchem mekudashot li b'kalkala
zu. So marrying those five women with the basket of figs, ואמרו
חכמים אין אחיות מקודשות, v'amru chachamim ein achayot mekudashot,
the sisters are not married. האחיות הן דאינן מקודשות, Ha'achayot hen d'einan
mekudashot, the sisters aren't married.
הנוכריות מקודשות, Hanochriyot mekudashot, it sounds like the other three women are
married.
היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case? אילימא דאמר כולכם, Ilima d'amar
kulchem, so if he said I want to marry all five of
you, and then it wound up that two didn't work for because
they were sisters, so את וחמור הוא. at v'chamor hu. If somebody
said like I want to marry you know like you and a
donkey should take possession of this. Okay, so if I try to
pass over possession of an object to two people, one of them
being a donkey, actually the original case in the גמרא Gemara is
one of them was a living person and the other was a
fetus that had not yet been born. Okay, and since I tried
to transfer ownership to both the person in front of me, half
to him and half to the fetus, and it doesn't work, because
since it doesn't work to the fetus, it doesn't work to the
person. So if the whole package doesn't work, it doesn't work for
any. Now of course here it's a little different, there the people
taking possession, here the people being possessed, but anyway, the גמרא Gemara
says it's like you and this donkey should take possession, ואת וחמור
לא קנה, v'at v'chamor lo kana, and then neither takes possession. So
here too, if I tried to marry all five and it didn't
work for two, it doesn't work for any. So why does the
משנה Mishnah sound like it still works for three of them? אלא
לאו, Ela lav, so the משנה Mishnah that makes it sound like
the קידושין Kiddushin works for those that aren't the sister, דאמר להו
אחת מכם, d'amar lehu achat mikem, it must be the case in
the משנה Mishnah is not I tried to say I want to
marry all five of you. It's I want to marry one of
you. Not exactly what פשט pshat of the משנה Mishnah is but
anyway. And therefore it doesn't work for the sisters, but the other
three are ספק מקודשות. safek mekudashot. One of the other three is
married to me, we don't know which one, but the sisters definitely
not. So what he does is because he claims that there's no
way it could work for the three if I tried to marry
all of them, he's reading the end of the משנה Mishnah that
I only tried to marry one of them, and then that's completely
consistent with רבא. Rava. I only tried to marry one of them
and nevertheless I'm not married to either sister, even though I only
tried to marry one. So וקתני אין אחיות מקודשות, v'katani ein achayot
mekudashot, the sisters neither of the sisters are married even though I
only tried to marry one. So לרבא קשיא רישא, l'Rava kashya reisha,
for רבא Rava the beginning of the משנה Mishnah is difficult because
it sounds like it's only because I tried to do both it
didn't work. ולאביי קשיא סיפא, v'l'Abaye kashya seifa, for אביי Abaye the
end is difficult, the end makes it sound like even if I
tried to do just one it wouldn't work. So the גמרא Gemara
says אביי מתרץ לטעמיה, Abaye metaretz l'taameih, רבא מתרץ לטעמיה, Rava metaretz
l'taameih, אביי מתרץ לטעמיה ורבא מתרץ
לטעמיה, Abaye metaretz l'taameih v'Rava metaretz l'taameih, אביי מתרץ לטעמיה ורבא מתרץ
לטעמיה, Abaye metaretz l'taameih v'Rava metaretz l'taameih, each one can explain the
other half of the משנה. Mishnah. אביי מתרץ לטעמיה, Abaye metaretz l'taameih,
אביי Abaye explains according to his reasoning.
המקדש אשה ובתה או אשה ואחותה כאחת, Hamkadesh isha u'vitah o isha
v'achotah k'achat, according to אביי Abaye it only doesn't work if you
try to do them at the same time. אינן מקודשות. Einan mekudashot.
אחת מאשה ובתה, Achat me'isha u'vitah, if you try to do only
one of them, או מאשה ואחותה, o me'isha v'achotah, מקודשת, mekudeshet, she
would be. If you said one and didn't specify one, then one
would be married, you wouldn't know which one, you'd have to give
a גט get to both, but at least it would work even
if you didn't know which one. ואם אמר, V'im amar, but if
he said explicitly, הראויה לביאה תתקדש לי, hara'uya l'via titkadesh li, I
will marry
the woman who I'm able to have sex with, in that case
אינה מקודשת eina mekudeshet and neither is married
because he'll be no way he'll be able to have sex with
either one.
דהוה ליה קידושין שאינו מסור לביאה. D'hava lei Kiddushin she'eino masur l'via.
Right, if you explicitly stipulated it has to be מסור לביאה masur
l'via it won't work. ומאן תנא נמי בחמישה נשים ובהן שתי אחיות,
u'man tana nami b'chamisha nashim u'vahen shtei achayot, and there's a story
of these five women in whom two sisters, וליקט אחד כלכלה של
תאנים ואמר הראויה
לי מכם תתקדש לי. v'liket echad kalkala shel te'enim v'amar hara'uya li
mikem titkadesh li. So אביי Abaye sticks into the last case, because
again the גמרא Gemara is now insisting exactly, the גמרא Gemara is
now insisting that the last case is a case where he said
only one of you. So since he said only one of you,
as long as we're going to stick that into the end of
the משנה, Mishnah, אביי Abaye is also going to stick into the
end of the משנה Mishnah that he said only one of you
who is fit for me, who I'm able to have sex with.
And in that case, אמרו חכמים אין האחיות מקודשות, amru chachamim ein
ha'achayot mekudashot, the sisters not. Okay, so אביי Abaye got rid of
the end of the משנה. Mishnah. I mean the end of the
משנה, Mishnah, the simple פשט pshat of the משנה Mishnah was like
אביי. Abaye. But since we insisted that the end of the משנה
Mishnah was one of you, אביי Abaye said well as long as
we're saying the end of the משנה Mishnah means one of you,
it'll also mean one of you who's ראויה ra'uya to me, who's
ראויה לביאה. ra'uya l'via. That's how he deals with it. The bigger
question is רבא. Rava. How does רבא Rava explain why the beginning
of the משנה Mishnah only talked about not being able to marry
two sisters at once? According to רבא, Rava, you can't marry even
one of them if you don't know which one. So the גמרא
Gemara says ורבא מתרץ לטעמיה. v'Rava metaretz l'taameih. המקדש אחת מאשה ובתה,
Hamkadesh achat me'isha u'vitah, don't read the משנה Mishnah כאחת, k'achat, at
the same time. No, if you try to marry only one of
a mother and a daughter and you didn't say which one, או
אחת מאשה ואחותה, o achat me'isha v'achotah, or one of a sisters,
נעשה כמי שקידש אשה ובתה ואשה ואחותה כאחת. na'aseh k'mi shekidesh isha
u'vitah v'isha v'achotah k'achat. It's like you did it at the same
time. So even though the משנה Mishnah says you can't do it
at the same time, רבא Rava is reading the משנה Mishnah as
basically saying if you try to even do one of them without
specifying... It's like trying to do it at the same time and
it doesn't work, ואינן מקודשות *ve'einan mekudashos*. ומתניתין נמי בחמש נשים ובשתי
אחיות ובקידוש אחד כהלכתו ושתיים ואמר הרי כולכם באחת משתי אחיות מקודשות
לי *umatnisin nami bechamesh nashim uvishtei achayos uvekiddesh echad kehilchaso ushtayim ve'amar
harei kulchem be'achas mishtei achayos mekudashos li*. And he said, behold all
five of you and one of these or any one or you
know actually here it's a little bit different it's not just one
of the five of you. Now we're actually nuancing it a little
bit different. Three,
all three of you plus one of these two sisters is married
to me. Okay. ואחת משתי אחיות מקודשות לי *ve'achas mishtei achayos mekudashos
li* בקידוש זה *bekiddush zeh* ואמרו חכמים אינן מקודשות *ve'amru chachamim einan
mekudashos*. So the three sisters yes, the three others yes, but the
one of the two sisters no. Okay, neither of the two sisters.
Anyway, bottom line is although the simple sense of the משנה *Mishna*
is talking about that you can't do two sisters at once, because
of the end of the משנה *Mishna* we're insisting that even one
of them doesn't work, so the end of the משנה *Mishna* supports
רבא *Rava*. So רבא *Rava* has a way of explaining away the
beginning of the משנה *Mishna*. Okay, so we have still this debate
of אביי ורבא *Abaye veRava* where according to אביי *Abaye* it's only
you can't do two at once, according to רבא *Rava* you can't
even do one if you're not specific which one. Let's try to
read one more case. תא שמע *ta shema*. המקדש את בתו סתם
*hamekadesh es bito stam*. אינה בוגרת בכלל *eina bogeres bichlal*. If I
marry off my daughter and I don't say which daughter I'm marrying
off, so my adult daughters are not included clearly because I'm not
empowered to marry them. הקטנות בכלל *haketanos bichlal*. But what it sounds
like is any of my of my younger daughters, my minor daughters
are ספק *safek* married. Okay, so Michael gave me a ring and
I accepted it on behalf of one of my daughters, one of
my non-existent daughters and I didn't say which one, so clearly he's
not talking about my adult ones but it's talking about one of
my minor ones. Well, one married? That's exactly רבא *Rava*'s case. Marrying
a sister and not knowing which sister you married. ואמאי *ve'amai*? Why
does that work to say that one of my daughters is married
we don't know which one? קידושין שאין מסורין לביאה נינהו *kiddushin she'ein
mesurin levi'ah ninhu*? ותיובתא דרבא *uvisyufta deRava*? It's a contradiction to רבא
*Rava*. אמר לך רבא *amar lach Rava*, so רבא *Rava* will say
to you, הכא במאי עסקינן כשאין שם אלא גדולה וקטנה *hacha bemai
askinan keshein sham ela gedola uktana*. No no no, I don't have
many adult and minor daughters. I have one adult daughter and one
minor daughter. And what it's saying is when I took the ring
it wasn't for my adult daughter it was for my minor one.
Of course that's pretty obvious. The גמרא *Gemara* says והא בוגרות וקטנות
*veha bogeros uktanos*, but בוגרות *bogeros* is plural. So it sounds like
I have multiple adult daughters and therefore multiple minor daughters. No, מאי
בוגרות בוגרות דעלמא *mai bogeros bogeros de'alma*. It means any adult daughters
that any person might have, but somehow it means in this case
you only have one. גמרא *Gemara* says אי הכי מאי למימרא *ei
hachi mai lemimra*? If that's true, obviously. I mean, what's the חידוש
*chiddush*? If the case was telling me that I had multiple minor
daughters and it worked, the חידוש *chiddush* would be against רבא *Rava*.
The חידוש *chiddush* would be one of the daughters is married we
don't know which one. But in this case of course I can't
marry my adult daughter I'm not empowered to. And if I only
have one minor daughter, of course he's married to her.
הא נמי לא חיישינן דשוויתה שליח
*ha nami la chashinan deshavisa shaliach*? Oh, so הכא במאי עסקינן דשוויתה
שליח *hacha bemai askinan deshavisa shaliach*. Now wouldn't we be talking about
a case that my adult daughter made me a שליח *shaliach* and
said, Dad I want you to find a nice guy and and
marry me to him. So I've been empowered as a שליח *shaliach*
by my adult daughter and I have a minor daughter. In that
case it's reasonable to think maybe I was marrying off my adult
daughter. Okay. מהו דתימא כי מקבל קידושין אדעתא דידהו קא מקבל *mahu
dseima ki mekabel kiddushin adaita dideihu ka mekabel*. So if I'm accepting
קידושין *kiddushin* I'm thinking because of my adult daughter she's getting older
already she's thirteen she needs to get a חתן *chosson* finally. קא
משמע לן דלא שביק איניש מידי דאית ליה הנאה מיניה *ka mashma
lan dela shavik inish midi de'is lei hana'ah minei*. No, I wouldn't
marry my adult one because my daughter one I'll get to pocket
the כסף קידושין *kesef kiddushin*. So obviously I wouldn't go with my
adult daughter first, I'd rather pocket the money that I get from
my younger daughter. The גמרא *Gemara* says anyways the גמרא *Gemara* says
like this, one minute. מי לא עסקינן דאמרה ליה קידושיי לדידך *mi
lo askinan de'amra lei kiddushai ledidach*? No come on, the case
presumably would include a case that the adult daughter would say Dad
marry me off and I'll tell you what you can even keep
the ring for yourself. ואפילו הכי *ve'afilu hachi* so the גמרא *Gemara*
says no even in that scenario we're not concerned I'll marry my
adult daughter first. Why? אפילו הכי לא שביק איניש מצוה דרמיא עליה
ועביד מצוה דלא רמיא עליה *afilu hachi lo shavik inish mitzvah deramya
alei ve'avid mitzvah dela ramya alei*. I have a primary responsibility to
marry off my minor daughters. Once she's thirteen she's on her own.
If I'm going to do it for her I'm just being nice.
Okay, but I really have to make sure my minor daughters get
married off, so I won't do my adult daughter before the minor.
So funny because logically you would say like like you say לא
יעשה כן במקומנו *lo ye'aseh chein bimkomenu*. Like if I have a
daughter getting older and one that's still young, I'm going to worry
first about the one that's getting older. Anyway the גמרא *Gemara* re-reads
it to be that scenario, so it's not a problem against רבא
*Rava*. But again the simple sense of a lot of this evidence
is against רבא *Rava*, that if you say one daughter and you
don't say which one or one sister, it sounds like it would
work. רבא *Rava* is insisting that it will not work, we're going
to continue with this tomorrow.